<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Joda Convert</title>
  <author>Stephen Colebourne</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="User guide">

<p>
Joda-Convert is intended for one simple task -
Converting objects to and from strings.
This is a common problem, particularly when communicating over textual protocols like XML or JSON.
</p>

<subsection name="Basic usage">
<p>
Using Joda-Convert is easy at the simplest level.
The main access is via the class <code>StringConvert</code>.
</p>
<p>
The easiest way to use the conversion is via the global constant:
</p>
<div style="border:1px solid black; padding: 0px 6px; margin: 4px;"><pre>
// conversion to a String
TimeZone zone = ...
String str = StringConvert.INSTANCE.convertToString(zone);

// conversion from a String
TimeZone zone = StringConvert.INSTANCE.convertFromString(TimeZone.class, str);
</pre></div>
<p>
In both cases, if the input is <code>null</code> then the output will also be <code>null</code>.
</p>
<p>
The global constant is quick and easy to use, but is shared between all users in the <code>ClassLoader</code>.
It also cannot be extended.
</p>
<p>
The alternative approach is to instantiate your own instance of <code>StringConvert</code>.
This would normally be stored in your own static variable, or made available as needed by dependency injection.
This may be updated by registering your own converters.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Converters">
<p>
Each instance of <code>StringConvert</code>, including the global singleton, includes a standard set of JDK-based converters.
These cover all the standard JDK types for which conversion to and from a string is sensible.
The set also includes JSR-310 types, but these are optional and loaded by reflection. The system will run without any dependency.
</p>
<p>
Each <code>StringConvert</code> instance, other than the global singleton, may have additional converters registered manually.
Each converter implements the <code>StringConverter</code> interface, which is self explanatory.
</p>
<p>
Converters may also be manually added by method name.
This is equivalent to using annotations, but suitable when you don't own the code to add them.
See <code>StringConvert.registerMethods</code> and <code>StringConvert.registerMethodConstructor</code>.
</p>
<p>
A converter can only be registered if one is not already registered for that type.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Annotation based conversion">
<p>
If there is no registered converter for a type, then a search by annotation is performed.
This will search for the <code>ToString</code> and <code>FromString</code> annotation on the type.
These annotations will indicate which method should be called to perform the conversion.
</p>
<div style="border:1px solid black; padding: 0px 6px; margin: 4px;"><pre>
public class Distance {

  @FromString
  public static Distance parse(String str) { ... }

  @ToString
  public String getStandardOutput() { ... }

}
</pre></div>
<p>
To be valid, the class must contain one <code>ToString</code> annotation and one <code>FromString</code> annotation.
The <code>ToString</code> annotation must be an instance method taking no parameters and returning a String.
The <code>FromString</code> annotation must be either a static method or a constructor taking a String parameter and
returning the correct type.
If the annotations are not found on the target class, then superclasses are searched.
</p>
<p>
The concept is that other open source libraries, as well as your application code, will implement these two annotations.
For open source projects, a key point is that adding the annotations is a compile-time only event.
The Joda-Convert jar file is not needed by your users unless they want to.
If they don't want to use Joda-Convert then the annotations are effectively ignored.
</p>
<p>
Joda-Time v2.0 and Joda-Money will both contain the annotations.
However, in both cases, the dependency is compile-time only, and not at runtime.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>
</body>
</document>
